Finding Aid for News and Information Services (University of Michigan) Audiovisual Materials
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
News and Information Services (University of Michigan) Audiovisual Materials1975-2012 1985-2005
University of Michigan. News and Information Services.
66.6 GB online
25 linear feet
87265.11 Bimu
The University of Michigan News and Information Services (NIS) acts as the University's media relations office, disseminating information about university programs, research, events, and faculty activities. This collection includes audiovisual recordings of press releases, news briefs distributed to television and radio stations, web-based podcasts and digital videos, and externally produced materials about the University and its activities. Additionally, researchers will find copies of University-produced media from the 1970s to the early 2000s in both audio and video formats.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The News and Information Services of the University of Michigan (donor no. 285 ) first began transferring its records to the Michigan Historical Collections in 1939. Periodic accessions have been received since then. The audiovisual materials presented in this finding aid were acquired in 2014. The podcasts were received in several accessions beginning in 2010.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open without restriction.
For the materials in this collection, the researcher should contact the Bentley Historical Library for options in regards to playback and reproduction.
News and Information Services (NIS) is the media relations office of the University of Michigan. NIS disseminates (to internal and external audiences) information about university programs, research, and activities of faculty and staff, primarily through the news media. NIS also responds to media requests for information about the University. Staff is comprised of information officers and editors covering specific university units, a photography unit, and a radio and television unit.
Although the Office of University Relations underwent several changes and reorganizations in the following years its founding, News and Information Services remained under its jurisdiction until 1998, when the office was divided into three vice presidential posts. One of these new posts was the Vice President for Media Relations, which was responsible for the University's News Service. In 2000, the Media Relations became the Office of the Vice President for Communications, which is where the current News Service resides in the University organization. News Service has continued to expand its media types and now includes podcasts, social media, and other online resources in addition to its print, radio, and television services.
The collection is divided into four series: Audio Materials, Video Materials, Audio Podcasts, and Digital Video. Each series has been further subdivided into subseries based upon content and then arranged in chronological order. For the Video Materials series, tapes of different formats have been mixed into collections in order to avoid a separation of like content, with the tape format identified.
The University of Michigan News and Information Services Audiovisual Materials contains sound and visual materials produced by the University of Michigan to share with the media as well as materials relevant to the promotion and image of the University. News and Information Services also publishes materials featuring achievements by scholars, recordings of speeches by invited speakers, and media appearances by or about University officials, programs, and scholars.
Subjects - Visual materials:
University of Michigan. News and Information Services.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan--Research.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Schembechler, Bo.; University of Michigan. News and Information Services.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan--Research.
Contributors:
Bollinger, Lee C., 1946-; Coleman, Mary Sue.; Duderstadt, James J., 1942-; Shapiro, Harold T., 1935-
Genre Terms:
Audiocassettes.; Digital audio formats.; Digital moving images.; Podcasts.; Sound recordings.; Video recordings.; Websites.
- Audio Materials
  The Audio Materials series contains the following subseries: The University of Michigan Commencements and Graduate Exercises, 1976-2002; The State of the University Addresses, 1980-1982 and 1988; Information and Technology Division, 1994-1988; Invited Speakers, 1983-1998; Martin Luther King Jr. Symposium, 1987-1999; Dedication Events, 1983-1994; Sporting Events, 1982-1997; Special Events, 1985-2004; and Audio Reel-to-Reel News Briefs, 1975-1994.
  - The University of Michigan Commencements and Graduate Exercises, 1976-2002
    The Commencements and Graduate Exercises subseries consists of 25 audio cassette recordings of commencement and graduate exercises and the speakers who addressed the graduating students. The dates of the recordings range from 1976 to 2002 but are not an exhaustive list of all commencement and graduation speakers within those dates. Content listed on the tapes includes the speaker, the date and semester of the event, and whether the ceremony is the main University commencement or a smaller event such as the Rackham school or LSA Graduate Exercises. Researchers will find additional recordings of University commencements in the video subseries within this collection.
    - Commencement: Winter 1976, Attorney Albert E. Jenner (Excerpts), Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Spring 1978, Vice President Walter Mondale, April 29, 1978, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Summer 1979, Rev. Jesse Jackson, August 19, 1979, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Winter 1981, University of Chicago President Hanna Holburn Gray, December 20, 1981, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Spring 1982, Governor William Milliken, May 1, 1982, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Spring 1983, Main Speaker, Chrysler Corporation Chairman of the Board Lee Iacocca and honorary degree ceremonies, April 30, 1983, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Winter 1983, Michigan State University President Cecil Mackey, December 18, 1983, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Spring 1985, Governor James Blanchard, May 4, 1985, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Winter 1986, Detroit's Hartford Memorial Baptist Church Pastor Charles Adams, December 14, 1986, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
      (Includes portion of a Regents meeting, 1981 interview with actor and fight director Patrick Crean, who was teaching a seminar at UM)
    - Commencement: Spring 1987, Mike Wallace, May 2, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Winter 1987, President Harold Shapiro, December 20, 1987, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Spring 1988, Soviet studies scholar Marshall Shulman, April 30, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Winter 1988, Nobel Laureate, poet Joseph Brodsky's Winter Commencement address; Joseph Brodsky news conference, November 18, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Spring 1989, President James Duderstadt, April 29, 1989, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Spring 1990, Cornell University President and former UM Vice President for Academic Affairs Frank H.T. Rhodes, May 5, 1990, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - College of Literature, Science, and the Arts Commencement: Spring 1990, Alumnus Lawrence Kasdan, May 5, 1990, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Winter 1990, Nederlander Organization President and former UM Regent Robert Nederlander, December 16, 1990, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - College of Literature, Science, and the Arts Commencement: Spring 1992, TV newswoman Carole Simpson, May 2, 1992, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Graduate Exercises: Honorary degree recipients include: Toni Morrison and Joyce Carol Oates. May 2, 1992, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Spring 1993, Hillary Rodham Clinton, May 1, 1993, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - College of Literature, Science, and the Arts Commencement: Spring 1994, Cartoonist Cathy Guisewite, April 30, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Graduate Exercises: Spring 1994, Detroit Mayor Dennis Archer, April 30, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Winter 1994, Surgeon General Antonia Novello, December 18, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Graduate Exercises: Spring 2002, University of Miami President Donna Shalala, Hill Auditorium. April 26, 2002, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Commencement: Spring 2002, United Negro College Fund President and CEO William H. Gray, April 27, 2002, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
  - State of the University Addresses, 1980-1988
    The State of the University Addresses subseries consists of 4 audio cassette recordings from 1980, 1981, 1982, 1988 by UM Presidents Harold Shapiro (first 3 tapes) and James Duderstadt (last tape) speaking at the State of the University event.
    - Harold Shapiro, State of the University Address. October 5, 1980, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Harold Shapiro, State of the University Address. October 5, 1981, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Harold Shapiro, State of the University Address. October 11, 1982, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - James Duderstadt, State of the University Address. October 3, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
  - News Conferences and Media Appearances, 1983-2001
    The News Conferences and Media Appearances subseries consists of 19 audio cassette tapes, which feature news conferences given by University presidents and officials, announcements regarding positions, anniversaries or commemoration of historic events in which the University played a role, gifts to the University, and contacts University faculty had with the media. The dates of these tapes range from 1983 to 1991.
    - December, 1983 College of Engineering news conference announcing agreement with Apollo Computer and Apple Computer to bring about $8-million dollars of new computers to the college at a substantial price reduction. December 1983 Dedication of Burn Center, April 18, 1985, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Jonas Salk News Conference for 30th anniversary of the Salk Polio vaccine, November 12, 1985, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Regents Public Interview of James Duderstadt; Naming of Duderstadt as President, News Conference, June 10, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - UM President James Duderstadt on WJR (Detroit) "Focus," June 13, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - News Conference: President Robben Fleming announcing Bo Schembechler as UM athletic director and Jack Weidenbach as senior associate athletic director. July 1, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - UM President James Duderstadt on WJR (Detroit) "Focus," September 8, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Gerald Ford, Jimmy Carter news conference at the Gerald R. Ford Presidential Library. December 5, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - UM basketball coach Bill Frieder on WJR (Detroit) "Focus," with discussion of his autobiography, written with Jeff Mortimer, December 8, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - FBI Director William Sessions' news conference; Sessions on campus to speak at the Law School's honors convocation, May 13, 1989, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Law school Dean Lee Bollinger introductory remarks, William Sessions remarks at the Law School's honors convocation. May 13, 1989, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Former President of Lebanon Amine Gemayel's news conference, April 5, 1991, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - News Conference: William Davidson's gift to found the William Davidson Institute; speakers include: Governor Engler, Senators Levin and Riegle, U.S. Treasury Secretary Brady. April 23, 1992 Tape 1 of 2, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - News Conference: William Davidson's gift to found the William Davidson Institute; speakers include: Governor Engler, Senators Levin and Riegle, U.S. Treasury Secretary Brady. April 23, 1992 Tape 2 of 2, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - UM President James Duderstadt on WJR (Detroit) "Focus," June 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Professors Peter Duren and George Piranian on their contacts with Ted Kaczynski, the "Unabomber," April 4, 1996, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Provost Nancy Cantor on WJR (Detroit) "Focus," April 3, 1998, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - John D. MacArthur Professor Emeritus of Physics Martinus Veltman news conference, after sharing the 1999 Nobel Prize for Physics. October 20, 1999, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Lee Bollinger, Tom Goss news conference announcing Goss' resignation, February 8, 2000, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - UM Interim President-Elect Joe White on WJR (Detroit), December 6, 2001, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
  - Information Technology Division, 1994-1998
    The Information Technology Division subseries consists of 24 audio tapes of materials produced by the University of Michigan's Information Technology Division between 1994 and 1998. The content of these tapes includes interviews with ITD members, services offered by ITD, and training material of ITD employees.
    - Jeff Tibbs, July 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Larry Gauthier NS, July 8, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Mike Clark, July 14, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Ted Hawss, July 15, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Ted Hawss, July 15, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Eric Aupperle, July 18, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Cheryl Munn Fremon, July 26, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - ITD Focus December 2, 1996, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - IIITD Focus December 2, 1996, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - ITD Focus December 2, 1996, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - ITD Focus December 2, 1996, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - ITD Focus December 6, 1996, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Interview with Jim Knox at ATCS, 1997, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Information Technology Video Interview: Eric Rabkin, June 24, 1997, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Information Technology Video Interview: Tom Finholt, Gary Olson, Eric Rabkin, June 24, 1997, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Information Technology Video Interview: Tom Finholt, Judy Olson, June 24, 1997, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Perry Samson Knowledge Communities Interview, June 26, 1997, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Mary Simoni #12, July 1 1997, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Working Group, Tape #1, September 29, 1998, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Tim Killeen Knowledge Communities Interview, Undated, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - ITD Tapes 18, 19, Nancy Butler Songer, Undated, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Knowledge Communities Video Tape #15, Richard Rockwell, Undated, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - #16 David Featherman, Undated, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Theo Bungan's / Purchasing, Undated, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
  - Invited Speakers, 1983-1998
    The Invited Speakers subseries consists of 13 audio cassettes and one Digital Audio Tape (DAT) dated between 1983 and 1998 that highlight important speakers who have come to the University for events not related to graduations or commencements. This includes Gerald Ford's appearances at events for the 1983 Campaign for Michigan Fund Drive, The Dalai Lama's 1994 visit, and Hillary Rodham Clinton's 1998 appearance for the Year of the Humanities and the Arts lectures and speeches.
    - Gerald Ford appearances at event for Campaign for Michigan fund drive. October 14, 1983, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Former British Prime Minister Edward Heath's public lecture during his April 1-7 tenure as Helen L. DeRoy Visiting Professor in Honors at UM, April 1990 (Tape 1 of 2), Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Former British Prime Minister Edward Heath's news conference during his April 1-7 tenure as Helen L. DeRoy Visiting Professor in Honors at UM April 1990 (Tape 2 of 2), Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - U.S. Surgeon General Antonia Novello speaks at School of Public Health 50th anniversary. September 21, 1991, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Mexican President Carlos Salinas de Gortari gives the William E. Simon Lecture in Power Center, with remarks by former President Gerald Ford preceding the lecture. Salinas was also awarded an honorary degree. May 27, 1993, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Introductory remarks to appearance by the 14th Dalai Lama in Crisler Arena. April 21, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Appearance by the 14th Dalai Lama in Crisler Arena, April 21, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - News conference with the 14th Dalai Lama in the Rackham Building, April 22, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Dalai Lama lectures to students in Power Center. April 22, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Associate Director for Science in the White House Office of Science and Technology M.R.C. Greenwood speaks in the UM Distinguished Lecture Series and National Science Policy in Rackham Amphitheater. October 3, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Lee Bollinger remarks, Hillary Rodham Clinton Year of Humanities and the Arts address in Hill Auditorium. April 28, 1998, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Hillary Rodham Clinton Year of Humanities and the Arts address in Hill Auditorium. April 28, 1998, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Jesse Jackson Taped rolled during videotape change in April 9, 1999 Hill Auditorium Speech, Audio Cassette (Box 1)
    - Marion Smith, Fredrick Douglass: Chapters 9-11, Edited Master, [Undated], (DAT Tape) (Box 1)
  - Martin Luther King Jr. Symposium, 1987-1999
    The Martin Luther King Jr. Symposium subseries contains of 19 cassettes from the Martin Luther King Jr. Symposium and Memorial Lectures. Ranging from 1987 to 1999, these tapes include speeches by Civil Rights leaders, activists, and politicians involved in the Civil Rights Movement and tributes to Dr. King's mission and life. Individuals speaking include Martin Luther King III, Andrew Young, and Willie Brown.
    - Representative William Gray III of Pennsylvania, Rev. Martin Luther King Jr. Symposium Memorial lectures, January 1987, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Civil Rights activist and former United Nations Ambassador Andrew Young's Martin Luther King Jr. Symposium lecture. January 1989 Tape 1, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Civil Rights activist and former United Nations Ambassador Andrew Young's Martin Luther King Jr. Symposium lecture. January 1989 Tape 2, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Andrew Young news conference, January 1989, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - California State Assembly Speaker Willie Brown news conference, January 1989, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Rev. Martin Luther King Jr. Symposium closing ceremony, Hartford, Conn., Mayor Carrie Saxon Perry, January 14, 1990, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Mary Frances Berry, Martin Luther King Jr. Symposium Memorial Keynote Lecture, January 20, 1997, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Martin Luther King III at Alumni Center, "Dialogue: Apathy Toward Activism: A Form of Moral and Political Suicide." January 21, 1997, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Nikki Giovanni, Martin Luther King Jr. Memorial Lecture, Hill Auditorium. January 9, 1999, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
  - Dedication Events, 1983-1994 (Box 2)
    The Dedication Events subseries contains 6 audio cassette tapes of recordings of various University Buildings Dedications from 1983-1994. Buildings included are the H.H. Dow Building, Solid State Laboratory, Kresge Business Administration Building, the UM Flint Science Building, The Willard Dow Laboratory, and the Integrated Technology and Instructional Center.
    - H.H. Dow Building Dedication; 1983 Solid State Laboratory dedication; Dow Building dedication, October 25, 1987, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Dedication of Kresge Business Administration Library and Computer and Executive Education Building; Dedication of addition to Tappan Hall, 1985, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Dedication of UM Flint Science Building October 20, 1988, Dedication of Donald Canham Natatorium, October 21, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Dedication of Willard Dow Laboratory, September 15, 1989, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Cancer Center / Geriatric Center groundbreaking, September 30, 1993, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Integrated Technology and Instructional Center (ITIC) groundbreaking; ITIC became the Media Union that is now the Duderstadt Center. April 14, 1994, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
  - Sporting Events, 1982-1997
    The Sporting Events subseries contains 5 audio tapes of mixed formats with highlights from UM Athletic events. Dated between 1982 and 1997, three of the tapes are programs from the Sports Talk show "Extra Points."
    - "Michigan Football, Run for the Roses," highlights of the 1982 season, narrated by Bill Femming, 1982, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Century Plaza band concert; Rose Bowl pep rally; salute by President Reagan; tribute to Anthony Carter, 1985, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Extra Points November 17, 1997, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Extra Points with Eric Mayes, November 24, 1997 December 8, 1997, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Field Hockey Pieces, Loveiete Wilkinson with Afi Mohamedi, October 9, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
  - Special Events, 1985-2004
    The Special Events subseries consists of 13 audio cassette tapes that highlight events, gifts, and celebrations of events at the University of Michigan. It also includes addresses by University Presidents, anniversary events of University institutions, and the inauguration ceremony for James Duderstadt in 1988.
    - Peace Corps 25th anniversary ceremony at entrance to Michigan Union, Vice President George H.W. Bush, October 7, 1985, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Memorial service for former U.S. Secretary of Health, Education and Welfare and former UM School of Education Dean Wilbur Cohen, 1987 Sides 1 and 3, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Memorial service for former U.S. Secretary of Health, Education and Welfare and former UM School of Education Dean Wilbur Cohen, 1987 Sides 2 and 4, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Public discussion among four UM presidents at Power Center, September 18, 1987, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - James Duderstadt address entitled "Focus", September 8, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Rackham Building's 50th birthday party September 30, 1988 (Sides 1 and 3), Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Rackham Building's 50th birthday party September 30, 1988 (Sides 2 and 4), Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - President James Duderstadt's inauguration ceremony, October 6, 1988 (Tape 1), Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - President James Duderstadt's inauguration ceremony, October 6, 1988 (Tape 2), Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - President James Duderstadt outlines the Michigan Mandate to an audience of Detroit civic leaders at the Renaissance Center in Detroit. November 10, 1988, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - UM Acting General Counsel John Ketelhut and Michigan Supreme Court Justice Dennis Archer outline the Michigan Minority Counsel Project to employ minority legal firm assistance in UM law cases. July 19, 1989, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - MDCH; Hepatitis C "Disease", "No Symptoms" [60 Second Public Service Announcements], March 30, 1999, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
    - Ceremony honoring Steven Ross' $100 million gift to the business school, September 4, 2004, Audio Cassette (Box 2)
  - Audio Reel-to-Reel News Briefs, 1975-1994